A thing I say to the team a lot is
context is everything. Especially in an
enterprise setting, just look at some of
our customers. So, you know, IBM is
using Slack. IBM is a 100,000 person
company. Salesforce is a 75,000 person
company. So, the context is huge. So, an
example of a feature is something called
AI Explain. You can now go to individual
messages and there's a message action
you can press that will explain the
message in detail. So, like that is both
a search and an AI problem where we kick
off a search to get more information and
more context, but then we're using the
LM to kind of create that synthesis as
well as bring in that kind of global
knowledge of just the context that the
LM already knows. Slack has always been
developed as a product-led development
cycle. So, I can see a future where
agents make this much easier. Like you
and I both have an idea of what we
should do with the composer in Slack. We
can go off and use our agents to build
up some kind of scrappy version of what
we're talking about so we can better
understand each other. How important
chat products like Slack are going to be
in terms of the way that we interact
with coding systems going forward?
[Music]
Before we jump into this episode, I
wanted to let you know that this podcast
is for developers building with AI at
the core. So, whether that's exploring
the latest tools, the workflows, or the
best practices, this podcast is for you.
Now, we've had amazing guests like
Olivier Pomel, the CEO of Datadog, Mati
Stanislawski, the co-founder of Eleven
Labs, Victor Riparbelli, the CEO and
co-founder at Synthesia, and of course,
Tessal's very own Patrick Dubois. And
they're all sharing lessons right from
the frontier of our industry. A really
quick ask, 90% of people who are
listening to this haven't yet
subscribed. So, if this content has
helped you build smarter, hit that
subscribe button and maybe a like. It
really does help us keep bringing the
folks who are actually pushing this
space forward and helping build that
AI-native future. All right. Back to the
episode. Hello and welcome to another
episode of the AI-native dev. My name's
Simon, your host for today. And joining
me today is Sam Messing, who's the VP of
engineering for search and AI at Slack.
Sam, how are you?
I'm doing great, Simon. I'm so excited
to be here. Thank you for having me.
Well, welcome. And today we're going to
have a a cool talk a little bit about
the journey of of how Slack has really
kind of revolutionized the way I guess
we
do business, but also now in the modern
age, how you know, the way that AI has
this role in in chat today through
through search and other things, but how
actually with AI-assisted
development and how agentic coding
relies so much on conversations and the
written word and how we can as teams
build applications, what role
an amazing communication team
communication tool like Slack can play
in that potential future as well. So,
there's a there's a ton to a ton to chat
about, Sam.
Why don't we Why don't we get started
with really just talking I think pretty
much everyone's going to know what Slack
is. Why don't instead of introducing
Slack, you introduce a little bit about
yourself and Slack AI? Sure. Yeah, so I
I have been at Slack now for 4 years. I
joined actually as an IC as an
individual contributor as as a back-end
developer.
And at over my time, I've worked on a
bunch of different features.
I have a background of about 15 years in
software development.
And so, I've always thought machine
learning and AI is very interesting. And
so, as I've gotten the opportunity to
start leading search and AI at Slack,
it's just been a dream job in terms of
getting to really be at the forefront of
those technologies. And within Slack AI,
the thing that we're really excited
about is, you know, a thing I say to the
team a lot is context is everything.
Especially in an enterprise setting,
you need to know what's going on. You
need to know what what your
sister teams are working on.
And alignment is a really challenging
thing especially at large enterprises.
So, you know, we hear a lot that
information overload is an experience
that lots of people are having right
now. Both just for the industry in
general in general with the velocity of
things and change that's happening as
well as within
individual enterprises where you might
have really really smart, charismatic,
intense people all working and
generating their own ideas. And how do
we kind of wrangle all of that? And it's
interesting actually because when we
think about like the the problems that
LLMs have with getting too much context,
you know, you don't need to go anywhere
near their their kind of like token
ranges before before you start seeing
degradation in terms of the quality of
the responses that that LLMs provide you
back. When when you're talking about the
the kind of like well, I mean, what does
the scale of like an an enterprise and
Slack look like? Are we
How much data are we really are we
really having to juggle here with with
with an AI AI bot here? Well, you know,
just look at some of our customers. So,
you know, IBM is is is using Slack.
Right, IBM is a 100,000 person company.
Salesforce is a 75,000 person company.
So, you know, the context is huge. And
you're right that, you know, part of one
of the most important things that we do
to develop our AI features is to think
about how do we manage that context.
Right, there's a new buzzword that's
going around around the idea of context
engineering instead of prompt
engineering. We take that very
seriously. And that's why also I think
search and AI are two really important
things to put together and to think
about in harmony with each other. And
you know, we discuss things internally
as is this search or is this AI? And you
know, a point I usually bring is doesn't
matter. It's all one thing at this
point. But we need to think really
seriously about not just what we do with
the LM, but taking care on what we bring
into the LM
to get that kind of response and and
accuracy. It's really interesting cuz
for me as a user, I don't necessarily
care whether it's search or AI so long
as I have that trust and confidence that
in the results that come back. From
from you as
you know, one of the folks who are kind
of like building these types of
capabilities in with search and AI,
where would you say the boundaries are
for where where where search has, you
know, a real ceiling that it can't kind
of like break through, but but where AI
really benefits and and and can can
deliver much better results? And and
what are the problems the other way
where search is actually far stronger or
far better at being able to deliver
results where AI just struggles? Yeah,
so
the first part, so where where does
search kind of hit its limits and where
does AI kind of shine, you're making me
think about one of our customers that is
a major
newspaper publication.
And one of the things that they've done
which I'm just think is so clever is
right, they have they they hook into the
Associated Press's wire service. Right,
so they get you know, these pushes. It's
essentially an RSS feed of every new,
you know, headline with 100 words on
what's going on so that they can help
orient their journalists to what's, you
know, keeping a pulse on what's what is
happening in the world.
Now, if you think about that as a search
problem, so now I have this channel that
has all of these push updates. And then
I search for something like you know,
what's going on in Bulgaria. I'm just
going to see tons of text and I have to
read all of those things and it can get
kind of tedious. And especially if you
think about search where we're trying to
focus on relevance rather than trying to
give you like the right longitudinal
kind of organization, it's really useful
to instead use something like our AI
Search Answers product which actually
synthesizes all of that information,
takes those raw search results, and
translates that into
an actual kind of human-understandable
text block with citations
so that you can go back to the relevant
messages, but you can
better get just a sense of like what
what is actually happening. I don't have
to kind of provide that synthesis for
myself. Now, on the opposite side where
where AI is limited and where search
continues to be kind of more important
is right, there it depends on job roles,
but one thing that we see a lot is there
are certain job roles where you need to
respond to every message that's coming
in and you need to understand what what
what is happening.
And so, that's where things like
structuring search results based on time
is a really useful use case. And so,
what we've heard from users is, you
know, the need to save searches and kind
of go back to these same searches as a
way to essentially triage where an LM
would that synthesis is not what they're
looking for. What they're looking for is
every single thing. Coverage or recall
is more important.
So, that's I think part of the way that
we're thinking about that balance. Yeah,
and it's interesting you were talking a
little bit there about almost like the
combination of the two a little bit. And
and it's very interesting even even
through kind of like a bunch of dev
tools without that that almost like need
a level of creativity versus a level of
accuracy where we see certain dev tools
that that use AI as well as looking at
an AI an AST or something like that to
provide them that accuracy of what what
a code flow is doing and then and then
layer AI on top. And it's interesting
that
you know,
is there this is there this path where
actually one or the other isn't actually
the solution, but we need this mix where
search is good at certain things, AI is
good at other things. Let's actually
combine them to actually get the best of
both. I mean, that's what we're we're
really focused on in general is trying
to use the both pieces of technology.
So, an example of a feature that we just
launched that I'm particularly proud of
is something called AI Explain. You can
now go to individual messages and
there's a message action you can press
that will explain the message in detail.
So, I use this personally whenever I'm
responding to incidents, right? I'm a VP
of engineering, I get
you know, mentioned in an incident
channel when something's going on, and I
have to quickly get up to speed. The
engineers are still actively working the
problem, and I don't want to slow them
down. So, someone sends a message with a
bunch of acronyms, maybe I don't know
those acronyms. What I would do in the
past is I'd have to ask someone, I'd
either be slowing down the people who
are really doing it, or I'd have to
bring more people in. But now I can just
use AI explain to catch up with what
their communication is about, so I can
understand what their acronyms are, I
can understand the details of why it's
significant without without interrupting
anybody. And that gives me a much better
ability as an executive especially to to
just get a pulse on what's going on
without having to interrupt anybody.
So, that is both a search and an AI
problem where we, you know, kick off a
search to get more information and more
context, but then we're using the LM to
kind of create that synthesis as well as
bring in that kind of global knowledge
of just the context that the LM already
knows and has, and and use that as part
of the
solution. Really interesting. We're
going to go on to talk a little bit
about how,
you know, the folks at Slack are using
AI internally as well. But before we
before we kind of like move move off of
the
AI Slack AI,
in terms of in terms of trends, I guess,
from from what you see as
real-world usage out there,
how how how much do you see people kind
of like you know, is is there a cliff
where all of a sudden everyone starts
really trusting and leaning into to AI
results? Where where do you see usage of
AI particularly? Maybe it's feature by
feature of certain things that that
developers and users are are enjoying
trusting straight away.
What can you tell us a bit a little bit
about the behind the scenes? Yeah, I
think
so what we've noticed is there are, you
know,
different features that are used by
different people as you might be
not surprised by. So, one of our most
popular features that I'm super proud of
is our message translation feature. So,
you can set it up to even be automatic
that if someone chats you in a different
language than your UI setting for the
language of the of the application, it
will automatically translate for you.
So, we can kind of accelerate that kind
of
communication. Obviously, there are
certain companies and certain
individuals at those companies that
really need to leverage that feature,
whereas other people, you know,
myself as an example, most of the people
I talk to were all native English
speakers, I don't really use that
feature as much. So, we kind of have to
think about those different job roles.
Another thing that we've seen is that
different customers are are at different
kind of
levels of adoption. And so, we have kind
of bleeding edge adoption adopters. Like
a great example is one of our customers
named Playtika. They have built using
Agent Force and the the platform of
Agent Agent Force to build proactive
customizable agents, multiple different
agents that take their their consulting
firm. So, take their sales people
through the whole life cycle of a sale.
So, they have a
call prep bot, a
analysis like a research customer
analysis bot, and then also a call
summary bot that happens at the end. And
those three agents work in parallel
to help individual sales rep basically
bring down their prep time for calls by
about 50%, and it's actually increased
their upsell bookings by about 50% as
well. And so, that's kind of like an AI
native company that is really going
aggressively into how do we build these
use cases and think about the
verticalization within our company. We
also see, you know, more kind of
tentative dipping their their feet into
the water features where, you know, we
have customers that will only try one
feature at a time and are really
concerned about change management and
understanding the boundaries with LLM.
You know, I think that I wish I could
tell every customer is the special parts
of Slack and Slack AI and Agent Force is
is two real main things. One is that we
have the context that you couldn't get
elsewhere. The communication is
happening within Slack, we can
understand at a much deeper level what
people are thinking about and what
problems they're facing. And then the
second one is deeply integrated is a
permission structure.
Right, we we built we are HIPAA
compliant. You know, we like we build
software for large enterprises that have
extremely tight compliance needs, and
that implies to all of our AI features.
So, you know, a concern that you might
have is that with search, you know, is
is an employee going to see things that
they shouldn't see or
and what we've really done, and I'm
really proud of this, is built a like
just-in-time permission layer
that ensures and enforces that people
cannot see or access things that they're
not available that's available to them.
And what we're expanding that to is
thinking about and providing enterprises
ways to
empower different job roles differently.
So, you know, if you you might want to
do something different with your HR
department as an example than you would
with your sales department. And right,
you need to think about those maybe not
so much as silos, but as, you know, like
protective communities that have both
their internal parts and then their
shared parts. And that's the kind of
thing that we're really focused on at
Salesforce and Slack. And that's a
really that's a really interesting
approach and and and tough problem,
right? Because I think being able to
kind of like guard that data and making
sure those permissions
are strictly adhered to is extremely
important. Is is that something that you
do is that something that you have a
guard in place then pre-sending
information to an LLM, or is that
something that you almost have a guard
based on the output of the LLM back to
the user? So, there there, you know,
it's a continuously developing
experience, and we're responding to what
our customers need and ask for. But yes,
we have permissions at different and
various layers. So, thinking about the
search experience, we start obviously by
only searching channels that you have
access to, but then we do a secondary
check at the end of the search to
double-check all of that because things
can change, right? There's always lag
time with skew, so we need to have a
real-time part of that. And that all
happens before an LLM gets involved with
anything. And it's important to note
that we don't do any generative AI
training, right? We are using
off-the-shelf LLMs. So, the way that we
provide that context is always going to
be through this permissioned search and
and kind of populating the context
window rather than, you know, what feels
much more risky to me, which is like
trying to train a model off of the
content because we can't Right, we as an
industry don't yet understand how to
control an LLM at that level. So, we're
just not even exploring it. 100% agree,
and I think it's like if you give
information to an LLM, you have to
expect that LLM to use that information
how it however it sees best, and it's
very very hard to kind of like have
gates post. So, I think the gates that
you mentioned there pre is really the
the the right way, the only way you can
really do that these days. Cool. And and
and with Slack AI, of course, coming up
very soon is is Dreamforce, which is is
it the week of the 13th of Yes, so
should be October 13th through the 16th,
I believe. But it's certainly that week.
And it's a big, right, Salesforce level
conference where we're going to
showcase lots of different new products
that we are developing. And I'm
particularly excited about some of the
things that we're going to announce at
Slack for Slack at Dreamforce. I can't
go into too much detail now, but let me
tell you that we're going to be
launching a very personalized experience
for individuals that will supercharge
their ability to use Slack
in a way that I I don't see anyone else
doing in the market. So, very excited
about that. That sounds amazing. Looking
forward to that. Let's jump in to how
you use AI within your development
processes at Slack. I understand you use
Cursor pretty heavily. Tell us a little
bit about that. You know, we
So, there's two things there that I
think are important. One is obviously,
we are an engineering organization, so
we want to use all of the the bleeding
tech tools that we can to build the best
software for our customers possible. But
also, we build AI features, and what I'm
excited about is I think developers more
than anyone else are furthest along in
the experience of understanding what it
means to work collaboratively with
agents. So, I am, you know, very focused
on seeing what everyone at the company
is doing with AI for development as a
way to kind of try and understand what
the future might look like for
non-technical. So, you know, focusing on
engineering, although I'd love to talk
to you also about other job roles at
Slack and how they use AI. We have
adopted Cursor as one of the the things
that we're trying, but we're also
experimenting with other other platforms
like Cloud Code and Windsurf, and we
have a lot of different things that
we're playing around with internally.
But one of the things that we focused a
lot on is how can we
integrate all of our custom software
tools with through via MCP.
So, you know, like any large
organization, we have built a lot of
different internal tooling around
managing experiments and feature flags,
around managing our data and analytics,
as well as managing things like code
search even, and making sure that that's
effective as possible across multiple
languages. So, the team has spent a lot
of time integrating and developing
internal MCP tools that we can use
through Cursor to kind of work through
those. To take one example, a challenge
that I had when I was in IC all the time
was, you know, someone would ask me
about a usage stat of something that I'm
working on, and of course, I should go
and write the SQL and figure out how to
do that. But before I can do that, I
need to know what tables exist and which
ones are real and we know the accuracy
of them and you know there's like you
know users underscore
final two cuz like there was some
migration a few years ago and there's
all this stored context that historical
context that's important to answer that
question. So we've built both a chatbot
that we call Jimmy
as well as an MCP integration to help
developers both explore and understand
what tables exist and how they can
answer those questions as well as
actually generate some of the sequel to
do that for them.
So that's been incredibly useful. You
know, it should be the case that any
engineer should be able to answer
whatever usage question you have about
their their features or what they're
responsible for and this is really
making that real especially for more
junior developers who just don't have
the context yet haven't learned as much
about the way the stack at Slack works.
It's been really useful for them. Yeah,
so so it's essentially giving agents
that
like whatever agentic versus whether
it's within cursor or cloud code as you
mentioned giving whatever agent
who is trying to perform a task the
context with the information it needs to
be able to perform that accurately
without hallucinating tables or using a
different version of the data or
whatever and then providing that
information back to the agent will allow
it to then you know, provide a solution
or provide a
sequel in this case a sequel query that
will that will access the data in the
tables correctly. Yeah, and what we're
seeing is you know, a lot of people are
using the cursor agent to understand the
code base and basically get to the right
knowledge to write the specific prompt
they want to get the agent to do the
right thing. Right, specificity with
instruction is really important when
you're interacting with agents.
Um
Luckily, I think one of the biggest
challenges for developers in their
career in general is technical
communication. Right, you can have all
the technical chops in the world but if
you can't sell people on your idea or
explain what you did, you're going to be
limited in your career on that and so I
see a real parallel between developing
your skills at communicating with agents
and this other part of career
development that is also super important
around just being able to communicate
specifically about technical topics and
understanding what level of detail to go
into for various you know,
audiences. Point and I think if we was
to take that broader and say
you know,
you're using cursor very very heavily
within within Slack. That obviously has
a big change in terms of how much code
gets generated what what pressure that
adds on other parts of the SDLC. What
what do you think I guess purely just
from the workload? What do you see as as
been very beneficial from those kind of
those kind of
efficiency gains that you'll get from
agents
and what is it also challenged you on as
a team in terms of
have there been new bottlenecks? Are
there things which actually might seem
very effective and proficient but maybe
actually in the long run took more time?
Like can you can you give us any
insights to how the the dev teams
fared with that? Yeah, definitely and
what I'm thinking about also applies I
think to non-technical roles but so
you know, by analogy.
So on the technical side some of the
places we've had the most success
is with things that are a little bit
more
wrote or a little bit more robotic in
terms of the the task. For instance,
right Slack like many mature
web products has started out in
JavaScript and we've moved into
TypeScript. And we've done what most
people do which is an incremental
adoption of TypeScript over time. So we
still have you know, old JavaScript
files that no one has needed to touch so
they haven't been migrated. That is a
big place where we've started using AI
and we've built
some scripts that use cloud code
essentially to accelerate people's
ability and you know, Slack has its own
particular ways of doing types and and
and you know, organizing our code and
things like that. So it's important to
kind of share amongst developers that
script that has kind of this built up
prompt of specificity to kind of get
over those
specifics or those quirks and now we
have multiple engineers running that
script at the same time. So in the last
six months we've got we've converted
more than 50% of our Java
legacy JavaScript into TypeScript and we
should be done in a couple months and
that's something that we originally
thought without AI would take you know,
two years to do just cuz you also have
to balance it with you know, asking
people to build new features or fix bugs
or things like that and so
another example is generating unit
tests. You know,
there's a lot of quirks with the way
that the unit test frameworks work and
especially for more junior engineers
they can get stuck kind of figuring out
details like non-interesting details of
how to set that all up rather than
focusing on the actual testing of their
their feature and so we've seen that as
a really great place for adoption. Now
where it's been a little bit more
challenging is you know, I've been
working with a principal engineer on a
prototype of an MCP client within Slack.
This is something that is very
speculative. We all think that we need
to experiment with this but you know,
it's going to be a long time before we
figure out exactly what that means for
enterprise compliance software.
He
Our back end is written in Hacklang
which is kind of built on
TypeScript is to JavaScript as Hacklang
is to PHP.
So so we use Hacklang and so there's no
MCP client in a you know,
SDK that you can use in Hacklang. So he
found one in go and he asked cloud code
please convert all of this to to hack
and he gave it access to our code base
so it can kind of understand what's
going on and then he just left it alone.
It churned for two hours and it came
back with a fully functional Hacklang
you know, implementation and he showed
me the PR and I was like this is cool.
This is a 5,000 line PR. I would never
let an engineer write a single PR that's
that big. Right, like um
So you know, it makes a huge burden on
the reviewer to make sure that they can
check all of that in. So then we had
this whole conversation of how do we
take this giant thing that got produced
and how do we actually go about
evaluating it and reading through it. So
I wouldn't say that that's necessarily
like a problem. It's just it's a
different way of working through the
code that we're still experimenting with
and you know,
figuring out how we can be successful
there. And as they say if you have a PR
with five lines difference, you'll
probably get 500 comments on it whereas
if you get a 500 line
PR, you probably get no comments at all,
right?
>> Right and you know, we're we're not
trying to do that. So Absolutely.
Absolutely. So so that's really
interesting like it sounds like you're
you know, you'll be
when we can when we can you know, very
reliably convert some of those more
legacy style applications and and and
code into into a more readable structure
a more tested structure
my goodness that that that that
certainly does give us so many more
opportunities and for
and maintenance burdens that that we
just you know, remove from ourselves. So
so
the moving I guess from one stack to
another modernizing certain applications
is a big one. You mentioned testing kind
of like adding resilience I guess to to
older applications as well.
I'm I'm super interested in the kind of
like the third one that you mentioned
there which was really the reviewing cuz
I think as you mentioned in in a just a
couple of months
perform a huge amount of refactoring or
or modernizing of applications.
We need to still be that have that
robustness to be able to say do you know
what? I fully trust this. I've I've
looked all through this. We've put all
the the reviews and the you know, the
code reviews and the checks and the
security etc. That almost becomes such a
such a big burden to actually do
effectively when a code changes are
coming so fast and and and
through so many different agents so many
different people. How do we how do we
even think about first of all us not
just becoming
uh kind of like code review bots
ourselves but also how do we how do we
maintain that that that focus really
and that
you know, with such a large amount of
change, how do we make sure our
levels don't drop our
quality of code review stays high?
Yeah, that's a great question. I mean
one I would say you know, I've always
worked at large companies that have had
very large code bases and you know,
thousands if not tens of thousands of
engineers working on the same code base.
So in some ways I feel like that
challenge has already been there in
terms of just the volume of entropy or
change in a code base and understanding
what's happening to it. So you know, in
some in some ways I think we can just
continue to leverage some of the
strategies that we've already developed
around both resilience testing when it
comes to you know, unit tests and
integration tests and things like that
and I think it becomes even more
important because
right, how do you know if your code
worked? You can read it but really
ultimately you have to run it and you
have to execute and you have to see what
happens.
There's other things there around
observability in terms of both noticing
what's happening in production and and
you know, that's a place that I think
we're starting to explore with AI as
well. So for instance, a thing that we
do at Slack a lot is we have you know,
we have a whole way that we structure
our channels so that they're kind of
semantically related to different topics
and one thing we do is if we have a
feature team, I'll take huddles as an
example. We have an alerts huddles page
and that our channel and that is where
all of the alerts that are related to
huddles will kind of surface and so you
can again use things like search answers
to kind of figure out what's going on
there and ask what what's happening
because it can get kind of noisy and you
can summarize that channel to really
understand changes over time. So I think
that's part of the the the the puzzle
but then another thing that is a little
bit more um
maybe subjective or a little bit harder
to kind of articulate is I think what
individuals need to do and how they need
to think about their role. Um and the
thing that I encourage everybody on my
team to think a lot about is um two
things. One is that critical thinking is
a muscle and you have to keep doing it
and you have to keep exercising it and
then two willpower is a limited resource
that you only have so much of in a day.
So you know talking about that 5,000
line PR, why does it not get any
comments? Because you just kind of run
out of steam as you're reading it and it
becomes kind of challenging. So we need
to both think about ways to be
selectively or we need to think about
what we're asking of our teammates but
also what we're asking of ourselves in
terms of making sure that we're getting
that balance right so that we can
spend the time on the critical thinking
but acknowledge when we need to take a
break and you know kind of pace
ourselves. So like a thing I say a lot
is right slow is smooth and smooth is
fast. Um you know and I think that it's
it's sometimes hard in this industry
right now at this moment to really lean
into that but I think that that's the
way we will develop the best software
and the most resilient software for our
customers. Yeah, completely agree. Let's
take a look at at the future and and and
think about how I guess two things. Um
first of all how development will change
but I'd love to talk about it from the
chat point of view really because um I
remember remember the old Devin days
that seems like a
an age ago when Devin first kind of like
announced what they were doing and and
what the first way that I certainly used
Devin we we we we use it at Tesla a
little bit in in some of our PR work and
things like that. But the way the way I
first used Devin was through Slack and
and we we got you know we we grabbed
uh we grabbed a trial or or a month or
two of of Devin and we started playing
with it as a as a development tool
whereby we chatted to it in threads and
we asked it to do various things it
provided us with uh with some a few
questions we had a discussion and then
it
spent you know spent some time
generating some code did some tests and
then gave us that code. Sometimes it
works sometimes it didn't and and we can
do that with new code we can do that
with alterations or adjustments to code
and and those types of things. And it
kind of it very much made Devin that
kind of you know uh programmer who was
on you know that developer that was on
your team which is really what they were
going for and I think why they very much
lent into you know Slack and and and
chat as the means at which to integrate
and interact with with tool.
Now obviously as organizations we use
Slack so many different organizations
use Slack uh around the world then that
the natural place for people to to talk
about how things should be built or or
what what we're building provide
information about things that are going
wrong or bugs those types of things
typically would be perhaps let's go into
chat let's go into Slack because because
that's where my team are that's that's
that's how I I have my contacts I have
my data and information.
Um we talked a little bit about this
stuff offline but I'd love to kind of
like talk through and hear your thoughts
on how important chat and
chat products like Slack are going to be
in terms of our the way that we interact
with with coding systems going forward.
Yeah yeah I have so much to say about
that. Um so you know the first thing I
would say is I challenge you on calling
Slack a chat app in the sense that the
way that we think about it is much more
like a work operating system. And what I
mean by that is the same thing as
literally a normal operating system it
is a collection of primitives that all
interact with each other that allow you
to develop something on top of it. In
the case of a normal operating system
that would be an application and in the
in the case of Slack that's an
enterprise that's a business. Um so
right we have we have yes chat and a way
to organize communication but we also
have things like huddles which is a
video conferencing tool lists a place
for you to put structured information
canvas a place for more kind of
unstructured thoughts and and like text
um and all of these things have deep
integrations with each other that allow
you to kind of build up context and
track context over time that is stuff
that we can pull into and interact with
natively through AI. So through agent
force you can build agents that actually
generate canvases or create lists or
even create channels as things go on. Um
with
Slack AI if you ask a question you can
pull in all of that information and grab
that and this is something that I work
directly on a lot is our enterprise
search offering of bringing even more
context. So between enterprise search
and work objects we are currently
working on ways that you can also
understand the context of other
applications that your enterprise is
using. So for instance I have an
proposal for a particular project I'm
really excited about right now. I wrote
it as a Google Doc I've shared it in in
Slack over time it gets tracked wherever
other people have shared it. So I have
the way as the in the work object to see
all of the conversations about that that
document even ones in channels I have
access to but might not be a member of
so public channels. So I can see how how
what I am thinking about is getting
disseminated throughout the whole the
company. That's that's kind of general
general abstract work like how we kind
of track all that together.
Bringing that more closely to
development what I'd say is I you know
it's it's not even that Slack would be
your future IDE I think it's more like
Slack is the future of how you build and
run and execute your enterprise as a
whole. So like we have this thing that
you and I talked about offline of this
thought exercise of what would it look
like to be a solo entrepreneur that has
Slack workspace with
10 to 100 agents that you use to kind of
accomplish your your job and you know I
have actually started to develop
a Slack workspace where I'm playing
around with this idea and so the way
that it works right now is I ask Cursor
can you make this change to the product
that I'm working on and then I have a
Vercel integration so a Vercel bot sends
in a preview link I can click the
preview when it's ready and see it right
there and test it and then I can go back
to my thread with Cursor and say you
know oh no you know you made it red I
really would like it to be black or
something like that can kind of have
this iterative experience. In addition
to that I've plugged in things like our
Perplexity which is you know an AI kind
of search product um where I can search
and ask about you know this this is kind
of a play example because I'm not
actually trying to start a new business
but like I think of it as you know what
my competitors would be and I ask for
details like what's going on with this
company what's going on with that
company. I forward all of those
conversations to one channel and now I
can use AI search to understand the
market and the industry.
We're still at the beginning of this and
there's still some edges here but you
could imagine a future where Cursor is
reading what other companies are doing
and other new
features are announced and it just
proactively produces new features for my
my application and Vercel lets me know
when they're available and then I can
see it and try it and then I can you
know use GitHub to say I need to file
these three issues and then Cursor
realizes there's new issues in GitHub
and fixes them and there's something
there that we're exploring and kind of
feeling our way in the dark toward about
how these agents all interact with each
other as well as with humans to kind of
supercharge the experience. Yeah yeah
and it's I mean it's like my
five times during that conversation my
mind just kind of like went off on a
tangent like oh that was cool what about
is this? Oh well that was cool what
about is this? And it's
a ton of these different agents that are
all effectively like owning their own
corners right? So you have Vercel for
the kind of like deployment you have
Cursor for the code generation and and a
number of others that are potentially
you know the code reviews and so forth.
But it feels like the plat you know you
you absolutely need that platform as the
knowledge base right? And today Cursor
is so far ahead uh in in terms of the
it's so far right for the fact that it
you know by the time you even go to a
Cursor all the decisions have already
been made all the docs have already been
written all the thought has already has
already happened and it's like now it's
it's about how good whoever is driving
Cursor is at providing the correct
messages the key decisions from all that
discussion that's already happened all
that context that already lives in in in
Slack and like you said the Google Docs
and things like that. And it feels like
we're probably missing a huge amount
that will actually really um
really provide that that that key
context as to how something should be
built and and what needs to be done
first and things like that. When you
said the one entrepreneur though the
solo entrepreneur do you feel like do
you feel like um
you know we would all be a single person
in a team and that team is agents or do
you feel like you know we in the in
going forward in the future would be you
know a small team of developers whereby
we are still leading the discussion
between us and then all these agents
would jump in at the right points. Do
you do you still see that kind of like
that team interaction and that that that
those those developer teams building
those building these these ideas
together or do you feel like it's solo
developers within these kind of like
very agent based
uh thought processes and then build
something that they then share with
other developers.
Yeah, I so, you know, I think of the
solo entrepreneur thing is just an
extreme example. Like let's take this to
a very, very extreme place and see what
that would look like. I think there's
lots of reasons why that is not probably
really realistic as a direction for us
to go in and I think we're always going
to have larger teams than that.
There's a few different reasons for
that. One is that I don't agents are not
human beings
and they can't replace human beings.
They are very good at certain things
right now especially. They're mostly
good at kind of more constrained wrote
kind of
aspects of tasks and so I see them more
as an accelerant where we can kind of
build up over time ways to reduce the
tedium of your work and and kind of
remove as much of that kind of red tape
or that kind of friction so that you can
focus on more of the kind of creative
aspects, right? Like
someone has to write the prompt. And
yes, agents can generate prompts for
each other, but what I don't think they
can do and I don't think that
um
they will do is is actually imagine the
future in the way that a human being can
and I don't think you can match human
creativity
and so you know, what I feel so lucky
about working at Slack is I work with
some of the brightest, smartest,
interesting people who all have very
different perspectives and it's through
that strength of diversity that we
actually get to the best ideas and so
you know, the thing that I could see
changing is right now for instance, we
obviously as I imagine most AI
developer companies are having. We have
some heated debates where we have really
strong opinions and we all disagree with
each other, but we're all right and so
it's really hard to kind of break that
analysis paralysis. The thing that has
worked for us is to admit that we can
talk till we're blue in the face, but we
won't know until we actually build it
and try it to know which direction feels
good, right? Slack has always been
developed as a product led development
cycle where we we really are just
passionate about our ideas and what
we're interested in is what does it
actually feel to use something that
you've built. And so I can see a future
where agents make this much easier. Like
you and I both have an idea of what we
should do with the composer in Slack.
Great, I can we can go off and use our
agents to kind of build up some kind of
scrappy version of what we're talking
about so we can better understand each
other and feel out which of these feel
good. So I think it can also accelerate
that kind of conversation and that kind
of prevent that kind of analysis
paralysis and and help the team move
forward. Yeah, pretty interesting. If we
if we look at the evolution that that
we've seen just in the last few years,
couple of years with yeah, okay,
originally the the the the first set of
AI dev tools that kind of more did very
good or reasonable
predictive kind of suggestions on a
single line, then we saw the multi-line
then it kind of like drove into agents
and you see them picking more and more
tasks or bigger and bigger tasks
that they can handle. When we look at
what this what this kind of like future
of software development
is going to is going to look like and I
agree with you, you know, we will we
will absolutely still have developers,
but what is this developer what what
will make a good developer in future I
guess both from the activities that
they're doing, what will they need to be
good at from the from the type from the
you know,
from the point of view of being able to
succeed at a specific task and and
secondly, what what are the core the
core things that if we could be better
at is it is it communication, is it
critical thinking, is it is it complex
problem solving? What are the key things
that we as as developers need to need to
be better at for this for this future
developer role?
Yeah,
very interesting question and I wish I
knew the future so I could just
tell you exactly what what what there
is, but you know, I think that the
skills that make the most the the best
engineers today will continue to be the
skills that make the best engineers in
the future, which is that they're
curious people.
They're empathetic.
They are critical thinkers. They're
self-reflective
and they're always evolving and
learning, right? We've had an industry
that has always had lots of disruption
and lots of change and it can be
challenging to want to kind of keep up
with it and to and to be kind of always
in a perennial kind of learning state
and I think remaining curious and
interested in playing with things is a
really important part of that. So the
biggest advice I give people on my team
is like make sure that you're trying
some of these things and you're asking
yourself how there are different ways
that you may use it and you know, an old
music teacher of mine when I was back
thinking I'd be a musician
taught me, you know, sometimes the best
way to practice an instrument is to go
to an art museum and look at art. And
that right just the idea that like you
got to you can't just do one thing. You
have to kind of have that plethora of
exploration and understanding
and that helps you in ways that you
might not be able to ever articulate or
really even see the through line, but it
will be there. Like, you know, I'm using
chat GPT a lot right now to help me play
Oblivion the video game, you know, it's
like I don't know I can't draw some kind
of direct line to what I'm doing
in my professional career, but like
there's something there. I'm using an
agent. I'm playing around with it. I'm
I'm thinking about these kinds of things
and
you know, so I think being curious and
really being open to experimentation is
probably the two most important things
cuz none of us know where this is going.
Yeah, 100% 100% agree. It's actually one
thing in Tessell we
we really hyper encourage people to get
involved in AI throughout their just
generally throughout their you know,
certainly the work tasks that they have
as well as as well as just more
generally. I think it's if you're
building AI tooling, the only way to
truly
be strong at that as you can is to
really immerse yourself in it. Know what
you like, know what you don't like, know
what other people other inventors are
doing in and around the space of AI so
that you could kind of like build all
that knowledge, build all that
understanding into the tool and you can
be a more empathetic to your users who
are going to be using these you know,
these AI tools as well. In in terms of
users,
do you feel like you know, the way we
build today our users are humans, right?
And and and people people will use our
use our tools the way we can kind of
like more empathize with because you
know, we use these tools as well.
The more and more agents get involved,
do you feel like we're going to have to
almost like have a separate a separate
kind of like thread or or swim lane here
whereby we need to build for users, but
then also we need to build for agents as
well. We need to make sure that agents
can consume what we're building because
they're going to build on top and we
need to make sure that they can be
successful as as part of that platform.
Is is that something as well that we
need to be empathetic to agents as well
as as well as humans?
Yeah, and we're already doing that.
And so some some concrete examples of
how we're thinking about that
Salesforce and Slack right we have Agent
Force which is an agent platform where
you can configure agents and now when we
build features at Slack, one of the main
questions we ask is how do we how would
an agent use this feature and how do we
expose those tools to I think they're
formally called actions on the Agent
Force platform, but how do we how do we
expose those actions to Agent Force? And
the way that we would expose things is
not necessarily the same. So like
another example is we are currently
working on and it's going to be released
for an early GA in October what we call
our real-time search API. And this is
really geared towards LLMs. So it's a
search API, so it's a way to expose
search, but it's focused on use cases
around bringing that content into LLMs
to provide you know, kind of agentic
experiences. So as an example, when you
we give you a search result in Slack, we
give you the message and you can click
on it and you can read the thread if you
want to. You just see the message. But
for an agent through an API, we need to
give it more context. So right now we
focused on things like the messages
around that thread
or you know, the full thread and things
like that, but we're developing and
experiencing and thinking about like how
do we teach it more about the
individuals and tell them who they are,
who works together, what their
relationships are, what their job roles
are. These are all things that we're
experimenting with right now. That won't
be part of the initial real-time search
API, but that's a thing that we're
thinking about in terms of how to evolve
it. So we're building those tools today.
Another place that you know, is a thing
that I'm really excited about that we're
only at the start of is a lot of our
agentic experiences and when I say our,
I mean the industry is really focused on
single player. You you know, you're
interacting with an agent just the two
of you. We have some ways that we are
starting to do more multiplayer
and that for us at least internally is
things like people write Claude.md files
for parts of their code base and right
and then right I can leverage the work
that another engineer has done
not even know they did it, right? But
the the agent experience is better. But
what we really are experimenting with
internally and there's some wild stuff,
but I don't know what's going to come of
it
is what is it like to have multiplayer
in channel experience with multiple
agents and multiple people all
interacting and reading and and talking
to each other at the same time and how
do we make that a value add rather than
like
a pile and just like you know too
overwhelming. So we have a bunch of
prototypes where we have agents that
automatically respond to questions that
are asked in a channel.
We have ones where you know, it's more
of an experience where you have to kind
of ask it to bring it in. But the
important part of those is for me is
it's again getting at this issue of we
have early adopters and then we have
people who are more hesitant or don't
even know that these features are
available to them. And so part of why
I'm so excited about bringing this stuff
into
channel is what I say a lot is show
don't tell, right? It allows these early
adopters, these fans to show how you
write a prompt and how you share it.
Like a feature we didn't get a chance to
talk too much about that we just
launched is our canvas AI feature, which
is really awesome, but it's still kind
of a single player experience. So you
can go into a canvas. This is what I do
every Friday. I I write a prompt that
says some write a document summarizing
everything I did this week
and group it by topic. And then on every
Monday I say read all my unread DMs and
give me a action plan of who to respond
to and what's the most urgent things for
me to respond to. Those are incredible
experiences, but you have to discover
that you can do that. So we're right now
experimenting with ways that we can kind
of template ties that or share that with
other people. So you know, if you were
my co-worker, I could be like here's my
prompt. You you can run it every Friday
too.
So those are kind of some of the
directions we're thinking about with
that. That's absolutely fascinating.
It's it's wonderful that you that you
that you've shared a lot of this with us
Sam.
We can talk for hours I know, but we
have to we have to roll up this episode.
So Sam,
coming up very very soon Dreamforce.
Sounds like there's going to be a lot of
super super interesting
things happening in the in the Slack AI
space for that. So so for those who are
who are nearby
or for those who who don't mind
traveling a little bit, why don't you
why don't you check that out.
Whereabouts is that this year? That'll
be in San Francisco. San Francisco
amazing. Yeah. Cool cool. And it'll be
in a various locations over a few days.
But please tune in for the Slack keynote
because I I really am so excited and
cannot wait to be able to talk more
about what we're going to announce. And
Simon, we should we should meet up
afterwards and and I would love to hear
more about your thoughts on what what we
announce. Absolutely sounds great.
Perfect. Thank you very much Sam. It's
been a pleasure chatting with you on
today's episode. Appreciate you being
here and thanks very much for tuning in
and listening and we'll speak to you
next time. Bye for now.